<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief discovery of the three natures viz., humane, divine, devilish, the rootes or originals of the politike states of Caesar, Christ, Antichrist in relation to a former treatise discovering the said three states, and withall farther clearing the usefulnesse thereof : whereby also is laid open to humane reason the impossibility of compulsive ecclesiasticall government to be of divine institution, and that liberty of conscience is to be allowed by all unto all, holding the bounds of civility, fully confirmed by principles in nature and Holy Scripture : humbly presented to the serious consideration of the High Court of Parliament / by Michael Quintine.</title>
            <author>Quintyne, Michael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13006</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13585414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13585414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 798:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief discovery of the three natures viz., humane, divine, devilish, the rootes or originals of the politike states of Caesar, Christ, Antichrist in relation to a former treatise discovering the said three states, and withall farther clearing the usefulnesse thereof : whereby also is laid open to humane reason the impossibility of compulsive ecclesiasticall government to be of divine institution, and that liberty of conscience is to be allowed by all unto all, holding the bounds of civility, fully confirmed by principles in nature and Holy Scripture : humbly presented to the serious consideration of the High Court of Parliament / by Michael Quintine.</title>
                  <author>Quintyne, Michael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A BRIEFE</hi> DISCOVERY OF THE THREE <hi>NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES;</hi> viz.
<list>
                  <item>Humane. <hi>The rootes or origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Politike States of.</hi> Caeſar.</item>
                  <item>Divine. <hi>The rootes or origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Politike States of.</hi> Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>Dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ſh. <hi>The rootes or origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Politike States of.</hi> Antichriſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>clation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a former Treatiſe, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the ſaid three States, and withall farther clearing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>neſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ereby alſo is laid op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to humane reaſon, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>bility of compulſive Eccleſiaſticall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> to be of Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Liberty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is to be allowed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto all, holding the bounds of Civility.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> confirmed by principles in Nature and Holy Scripture: Humbly preſented to the ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the High Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Michael Quintine.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will put enmity between thee and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and thy ſeed and her ſeed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iam. 2.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>So ſpeak yee, and ſo doe, as they that ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the Law of Liberty.</p>
            </q>
            <p>London Printed. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100526:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100526:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH COURT Of Parliament now aſſembled within his Majeſties Realme of England, be all rightneſs of ſpirit, the root of irreprove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deſigns, and proſperous correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſucceſſe, in all matters pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to godlineſs, State, &amp; Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in every reſpect.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Formerly committed to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this moſt Honourable Aſſembly, a Treatiſe containing a briefe diſcovery of the <hi>Civill,</hi> true <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> and falſe <hi>Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call States,</hi> in the eſſentiall and maine circumſtantiall parts of each body or ſtate, being the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act way to diſcover and rectifie grievances in any State of Policy, whereby God and <hi>Caeſar</hi> may have their due; for the accompliſhment whereof, and further clearing the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of what is therein contained, I doe humbly begge your impartiall Examination of the enſuing paſſages, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently manifeſting from whence theſe ſaid ſeverall Policies do ſpring or ariſe; and confirming withall what is already proved by the ſaid Treatiſe touching the great abuſes done
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100526:3"/>to the Church of Chriſt and Civill State, by the falſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall State or Kingdome of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>All things have their begining and ending from God as the Primary cauſe of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</p>
            <p>Alſo all things have their being through Secondary, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or inſtrumentall cauſes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.16, 17, 18.19, 20.</p>
            <p>The roote and ground of Policie is Nature Divine, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, or Devilliſh, it is properly of uſe to none but ſuch creatures as participate of an immortall ſpirituall ſubſtance. All things under the degree of humane nature are uncapable thereof, and all other immortall ſpirits are inviſible, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the whole Creation in all ages paſt, preſent, and to come.</p>
            <p>Mankinde, or humane nature in the condition ſhe now ſtandeth, under the curſe, being thereby made liable through mercy of redemption unto ſalvation, and through wrath of reprobation unto damnation, is ſubject unto a threefold Politicke Government, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Humane or Civill Government, or the Policie of Magiſtracie, which concernes men in ordering of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and eſtates, which ariſeth from the Law of the nature of man, in man, towards man in the ſtate of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</p>
            <p n="2">2. True Eccleſiaſticall State or Kingdome of the Goſpell, the viſible government of Jeſus Chriſt, who ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> in Divine Policy, which iſſueth from the Law of the divine nature, which is perfect love, as is teſtified in the Sonne of Love, the ſalvation of Mankinde.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And falſe Eccleſiaſticall State or Kingdome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, devileſh or viſible Government of the ſonne of pride, which in ſpirituall politique juriſdiction exalteth himſelfe above all that is called God, or ſaid to be of God, in matter of policy, ſitting in the Temple of God (which is conſcience) as God, &amp; ſubjecting, or ruling over the ſame by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100526:3"/>compulſion the portion, of fooles and unreaſonable men, for it loves oppoſite, and preventeth any courſe of nature, which floweth from the Law of the ſpirit of envy, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the devill, the father of lies all miſchiefe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe three States of Policy of which I have formerly treated more at large, the holy Scripture and common or humane reaſon ſhew forth in a lively manner, iſſuing from the three natures; namely, Humane, Divine, and Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</p>
            <p>To the true and ſubſtantiall diſcovery of the which three natures the rootes of Policie, and how they are joyntly conſiſting in man without intermixion and interpoſition of contraries; I ſhall in this Treatiſe moſt chiefely and briefely addreſſe my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Humane nature, or the nature of mans body, his elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary or fleſhly part of his eſſence (which eſſence conſiſteth of fleſh and ſpirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22.23.)</p>
            <p>Thou art conſiderable, and likewiſe the whole man, in a two-fold State and condition. As created, or redeemed; as fallen, and under the curſe.</p>
            <p>The nature of the ſprituall part of mans eſſence will be diſcovered in ſetting forth the divine, and divilliſh nature, ſpirit, or diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>The nature of mans humane part in the created ſtate, as the Morrall Law of God, and the perſon of Chriſt doe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, was without ſinne, made righteous according to the Image of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.17. And according to the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or nature then in man, towards man, out of the law there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (which is the ordinary meanes through Gods favour and mercy of the generall preſervation of mankinde) ſpringeth civill Government or Magiſtracie, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>But ever ſince <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were ſnared with an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious temptation, and would be wiſe without allowance, they drew a curſe upon their humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture themſelves, and throughout all their poſterity, even to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100526:4"/>the end of the world, and ever ſince they taſted of the tree of Knowledge of good and evill, which was forbidden, they and theirs in the humane part have alwayes loved e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill more then good, which is an infallible teſtimony of a curſed change in the nature of humanity.</p>
            <p>Therefore Humane nature, Take notice that thou art now ſince thy fall in thy Elimentary conſtitution curſed, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous, and averſe to any good, inclining to the nature of the Angells, who left their firſt eſtate, and art become plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in nothing more than the exerciſe of pride, deceit and envie; an Humoriſt, ſeeking thy ſelfe, although to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thy ſelfe, and all that have or may have any relation unto thee; thus much hath the whole race of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde (except the Sonne of God himſelfe) manifeſted, plainely expreſſing an undeniable effect of the curſe, the unruly and exceeding predomination of one element or other in the ſaid nature, this is the nature of the humane or bodily part of man, no civill calling but redemption ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted any man in any meaſure, common experience is witneſſe enough, beſides holy Scriptures confirmeth the truth thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10. to <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. Notable proofe alſo hereof is the Scripture diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the throne of affections, the principle part in the body of man, and may well be taken for the whole man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.19. had not God out of his love in generall to man given the State of Magiſtracie, which was for reſtraint of the unrulineſſe of mans humane nature. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3.4.1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.10. what difference would there appeare betweene earth and hell, only in caſe of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, of evill and miſery; the humane nature being thus ſubjected under the power of juſtice, God is free in the compaſſion of his love, to beſtow his Spirit and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where he pleaſe, and in his wrath and diſpleaſure to reject and caſt away whom he will; who, and what ſhall contend with his Maker. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20, 21.</p>
            <p>The nature of the ſpirituall ſubſtance, the immortall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100526:4"/>ſoule, the formall part of the eſſence of man, it iſſueth from God or the devill, and is one of the ſaid two Fathers or Fountaines of Spirits, and it will be ſufficiently ſet forth in the diſcovery of their natures.</p>
            <p>But that the ſoule of man receives his being, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipateth in nature, as aforeſaid; take a few proofes from principles in Nature, and Poſitive truth of Divine Writt.</p>
            <p>Man begets a Sonne in his owne likeneſſe in the nature of his materiall ſubſtance, but the often contrarietie in the ſpirits of parents and children, as godly parents, and wicked children, wicked parents and godly children, the unlikeneſſe in that part proveth them no ſoule Parents.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe in caſe Parents ſhould beget ſoules, when as often times the father and mother are contrary in nature of ſpirit what ſhall be their Off-ſpring in that reſpect?</p>
            <p>The Scripture ſheweth plainely that the children of God in reſpect of their ſoules, and the nature of them are ſaid to be borne of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. God is called the Father of them in reſpect of that part of their eſſence, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16. and <hi>ver.</hi> 48. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. Chriſt cleareth this point to the full, diſcovering the Fountaine or Father of the ſpirit of the Jewes, who went about to kill him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.42. and 44. and in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. the Holy Ghoſt tearmes our naturall parents Fathers of our fleſh, and God the Father of Spirits.</p>
            <p>The divine nature, ſpirit, qualitie, or diſpoſition of God (which moſt specially of any part of his eſſence ſets him forth to be what he is, the onely and abſolute good, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.17.) is infinite love, every part of the whole creation doth teſtifie the truth thereof, which he made not to ſupply his owne want; the continuall ſupply of the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wants of the whole earth doth the ſame, the great mountainous worke of love never to be forgotten by the ſonnes of men, the giving of the price of Redemption, his onely begotten ſonne, his expreſſe Image, who laid downe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100526:5"/>his life for his people, fulfilling the will of his Father, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16, 17. A teſtimony without exception, proving the nature of God to be infinite, and matchleſſe love, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. The nature and qualitie of all things is the moſt eminent part of their eſſence, and ſo it is the moſt pernicious part by which God is made knowne to the ſonnes of men, for his nature or ſpirits ſake, which is love, hee is called love, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16. for a teſtimony hereof alwayes to ſtoppe the mouthes of lyers, and their father (whoſe envie would cloud all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God towards poore men) beſides the ſtate of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Policy, God hath from <hi>Adam</hi> unto this day from time to time inſtituted a ſtate of Divine policy, in publike teſtimony and viſible acknowledgement of the fellowſhip which he hath with his redeemed ones; and now according to the fulneſſe of time, manifeſting the fulneſſe of his love in paying downe the full price of Redemption, the perfection and full accompliſhment of the worke of ſalvation; of his divine Nature which is perfect love and goodneſſe, he hath inſtituted a viſible ſtate of divine Policy, for the ſonne of his Love, the Captaine of ſalvation, and his people of Love here upon earth, which is compoſed of love; not onely for matter and forme, but alſo in reſpect of ſtate and platforme, and the Lawes and Ordinances thereof; upon what can man thinke or looke, and not ſee the tender mercies of God over all his workes? <hi>Pſal,</hi> 145.9.</p>
            <p>And that the Nature, Spirit, or diſpoſition of the whole Hoaſt of God, both men and Angels is Love, the Word of God cleareth it experimentally by the miniſtring of the Angells, and by the Morrall Law of God, both Tables written in the hearts of men which are made partakers of the divine nature, for by love is the ſame fulfilled, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13.</p>
            <p>The nature, Spirit, or diſpoſition of the Divell, (from whom every baſe ſpirit deriveth his meaſure of unnaturall lewdneſſe, both men and Angels of the deviliſh broode) is infinite envie, Loves oppoſite, the firſt Act that ever the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100526:5"/>devill did unto mankinde, proveth the truth thereof, for in his hopeleſſe deſperate fallen eſtate, without any expectation of reliefe to himſelfe, he treacherouſly deceived man in the time of his innocencie, and by deluſion and flattery through rebellion againſt his Maker drew him into the thraldome of ſinne and miſery, notwithſtanding it could be no abatement to his owne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. and ever ſince man hath ſubſiſted in an hope of redemption from time to time, and in ſundry ways, hath the nature of the devill beene largely expreſſed to be envie her ſelfe, which is alwayes ſo ready to worke miſchiefe that ſhe pines at the good of any; witneſſe the caſe of <hi>Adam, Abel</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> yea all of note for uprightneſſe upon record in Scripture from age to age, farther teſtimony hereof is, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p>The ſeverall ſtates of Policy which God did opportunely inſtitute in the world for the good and comfort of men, the upright in ſpeciall, againſt which none but the nature of the devill, boundleſſe envie could except, or vilifie them; yet the chiefeſt of them hath ſhe undervalued, and by deluſion hath drawne the chiefe of the earth in the ſtate of civility, and the greateſt part of temporizing ſubjects thereof, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to tread the ſame under foote, and all that apparantly incline thereunto; and hath cauſed the earth, the great ones, &amp; greateſt part therof to ſet up, countenance, and ſupport a ſtate of Tyranny in matters of conſcience, wherein is diſorderly forced together with violence divine and civill things, to the confuſion of both the ſervice he willeth and delighteth in, even the utter undoing of the whole earth: In the time of the ſtate of the Jewes which God ordained as a great light to ſhew the world that he had viſible fellowſhip with ſuch as feare him, and to preſerve them in holineſſe: then and therein how did the envie of the devill, and his crew ſhelter ſuch oppreſſion, and groſſe abuſe of Gods holy things, which grew to ſuch an height of hipocriſie that they were not aſhamed without Law or Reaſon, yea contrary to both, to put to death equity, yea Love himſelfe, the very
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100526:6"/>Sonne of God, whom none could convince of ſinne, which effected the confuſion of their houſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. and ſince the deſolation thereof, and Gods election of the Kingdome of his Sonne, in the ſtate of love, compoſed of matter and forme of love, Subiects won by love, Volunteers, worſhipers in ſpirit and truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23, 24. How hath matchleſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie beene palpably manifeſted to be the nature of the devill, who to confound mankinde in all wayes, by his deluding feates and wiles hath brought in faſhion in all parts of the earth, violent and compulſive government of conſcience, knowing, whileſt that continueth, humane race, eſpecially the moſt upright and innocent muſt to wracke, for who in conſcience can governe or be governed by humane power, but for civilities ſake, except ſuch men as can, to gaine the world, and preſent welfare of their fleſh, ſubject conſcience to any thing, excuſing themſelves upon the unjuſt deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded charge of others, who, for all their great takings upon them; have as much to doe in that reſpect to give account for themſelves as they; the truth of this diſcovery is plaine enough by experience, that the nature of the devill is infinite envie, if men would looke into it: but what ſhall I ſay, if our firſt Parents in the time of innocencie were ſhort ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, well may their poſterity conceived in ſinne, and brought forth in iniquitie be blinde.</p>
            <p>And that the nature, ſpirit, and diſpoſition of the helliſh rabble, the whole company of devilliſh men and Angells is envie, the ſame with the devills, their ſpirituall Father, See <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>That the eſſence of man conſiſteth of a two-fold ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, is formerly proved, the nature of his humane part, and the nature of his ſpirituall ſubſtance (being derived from God or the devill) together with the nature of them alſo, is likewiſe ſet forth, which three natures are alſo diſcovered to be the ground and roote of Policie: The next thing inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and promiſed in this Treatiſe is, to lay open how two natures are conſiſting in man without intermixtion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100526:6"/>of contraries, which in any height of meaſure is the meanes of confuſion in any creature.</p>
            <p>By the way it falleth to my hand to ſpeake of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the conſtitution of humane nature in the firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was without ſinne, and whereunto all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures beſides were made ſubiect and inferiour, both in the nature of their conſtitutions, government, and uſe, which humane conſtitution alſo was made ſerviceable (being the ſubiect part of man) to the right ſpirit which God breathed into him, whereby man became that compleate creature in both parts, the diſcription of whoſe nature in both reſpects is the Morrall Law of God, whoſe lively, or rather living Image was the onely begotten Son of God, that quickning ſpirit, Jeſus Chriſt, the Redeemer of what was loſt in and by man, in, and for all the Elect and choſen ſeede of <hi>Adam,</hi> but for brevitie ſake, I ſhall omit to ſpeake any more of it, and according to my purpoſe, indeavour to ſhew how the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of man conſiſteth of a two-fold ſubſtance without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition of contrary natures.</p>
            <p>Man conſidered as formerly, created, and fallen, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and under the curſe, the Law of Juſtice holds him liable to love and wrath, ſalvation and reprobation, and to be made a veſſell of honour and diſhonour without any wrong and injuſtice at all.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of man as created in righteouſneſſe, &amp; as redeemed from all iniquitie, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. whereby righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is imputed, and man becomes as made without ſinne, is both one, if any difference be in caſe of priviledge; redemption affords the greater, making ſtronger the union by the meanes of reconciliation, wherein the redeemed are indeered unto God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. to 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. &amp;c. And God is the like unto them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. from 13. to 20. The caſe ſtanding thus betweene God and man by redemption, whereby the humane part of man is made or become as at firſt, a ſubiect or materiall veſſell for a divine, reaſonable, or living ſoule; and although full of frailty and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100526:7"/>infirmity as all elementary and mortall bodies, as alſo as earth and droſſe it ſelf in compariſon of any divine ſpirituall ſubſtance, which as it is in it ſelf, is void of any divin uſe, yet ſuch as God in his wiſedome is pleaſed to make part of the eſſence of man, which ſetteth forth the glory of redemption, and the power of Chriſt in the work of ſalvation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. &amp; ſo man in his conſiſtance of ſoul and body, fleſh &amp; ſpirit, is imputed as in firſt creation without ſin, and ſaid to be born of God, &amp; not to commit ſin, as God accounts of his children through re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9, 10. And thus the two Natures, Divine and Humane are conſiſting in man, without intermixion of contraries; though through infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the fleſh, ſubject to naturall corruption, temptation of the devill, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of the men of the world, againſt which they warre, untill the perfection of the redemption of the body doe appeare, even untill Mortality hath put on Immortality.</p>
            <p>Man conſidered fallen, and under the curſe, is a correſpondent ſubject for the devill, being both inclineable to confuſion, and the way of deſtruction, as is ſet forth in their ſeverall natures; theſe are the enemies Tares which he ſowed amongſt the good ſeed, theſe grow together in the world untill the harveſt of God; I need not ſtand to relate the meanes of their union, nor the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thereof, the world in all parts, every day yeelds plenty thereof; what doth God reprobate, but the devils own; the union it ſelfe of the nature of man, and of the ſpirituall ſubſtance which he receiveth from the devill, as the father there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is all one by way of infuſion, with that of God and man, differing only in nature and ſubſtance, and the end thereof: Thus contrary to the two-fold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of the eſſence of the redeemed is this of the curſed, without contrariety in nature of both parts, but not without mans confuſion, becauſe in this caſe the poore creature Man, is made a ſlave unto the worſt of creatures, whereby his being and end becomes more vile and miſerable than the moſt inferiour crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which God formed out of the earth.</p>
            <p>This once more, with my heart in my hand, in the ſight and diſcovery of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the fountaines of Policy for the truths ſake, which is the way of all mans reall happineſſe; Muſt I ſpeak unto this high Court, which guideth the Raines of the power of all the State of this Land; If the ſtrength of the devils envy through deluſion was too hard for you Parents in the time of Innocency in their nature, and hath ſince their fall prevailed againſt divers of their poſterity, both by deceit and violence, to the confuſion of them in reſpect of matters ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and temporall; Conſider ye civill powers, and yet children of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> yea, and ſince the curſe are ye not as liable to be corrupted in your policy, which is but the image of their nature, both in the nature, uſe, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice thereof; may not ye ſubſcribe to devilliſh adviſe, reaching after more and higher dominions than God hath given you, and make what is your own,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100526:7"/>an inſtrument of confuſion, in imploying it out of bounds, to the deſtruction of innocent bodies, which is worſhipping the devill, and an effect of the curſe upon mankinde; ſuch practiſe hath been the lot of many Nations and particular perſons, witneſſe your own experience; Why doe ye as parents of ſoules and ſpirits meddle in the command of conſcience, and ſupport ſuch as doe, with ſword and maintenance; is it typicall, as in the time and ſtate of the Jewes, or as if Chriſt were not riſen from the dead, or doe you thinke God accepts of more than he requires at your hands, or will you make an intermixion, one head of two bodies, or two heads of one body, which cannot be otherwiſe, if Church and Common-wealth be all one, or being as two under one head, which nature and policy both deny, in Scripture and common reaſon; will ye work your own confuſion, in taking Gods work upon you, in making wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers in ſpirit and truth, for ſuch only God requires, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.21, 22, 23, 24. which by compulſion you muſt doe, or make hypocrites; can ye draw men to Chriſt in Spirit or Policy, which is not in your power, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.44, 45, 46. or will ye who ſhould provide for the ſtrength of the Law of humanity, breake the Law of Charity belonging to conſcience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. This great ſpirituall State of juriſdiction now in faſhion, or any that is like to be of the conſtitution of compulſion (which jumbleth and tumbleth together the fineſt natures, and ſouleſt worſhip, Gods Divine and holy Ordinances with fouleſt and profaneſt natures (which will one day coſt confuſion of ſoules and blood enough) were it not for the great temporall revenewes entailed upon her, ſhee would not in humane reaſon and common equity be ſo much ſtood upon, and contended for, for thoſe that goe about to yoke others conſciences, would not bee ſerved ſo themſelves, except they be devils incarnate, and will become any thing in Religion to ſerve covetous ends; Bondage of conſcience is the groſſeſt ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and moſt devilliſh captivity upon earth, from whence ſpringeth the greateſt treachery, and moſt dangerous rebellion which the earth can afford, yee may beleeve it when ye ſee it; All liberty within bounds of civility incourage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and begets a rich Nation, hindereth not prevention of dotage, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand conveighance of eſtate to forraigne Belly-gods, who by flattery, rob people ſtronger in zeale then knowledge, of their bodily means of ſafeguard, and load their ſoules with an increaſe of unnaturall ſlavery, even to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. So hoping of the true effect of upright dealing with God and Man, the ſight of that liberty of truth which bringeth peace, ſtrength and ſafety to all Lands and people of Innocency: I remaine Gods and Yours, in all due ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to my power.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. Q.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100526:8"/>
            <head>Now followes the Reaſons and Motives that ſet me upon this Worke.</head>
            <p>NOt long ſince I commended to your Highneſſe, and the Parliament, one Treatiſe containing an eſſentiall diſcovery of the States of Policie as they are diſtinct one from another. And another ſince of the Natures likewiſe from whence they ſpring; both which in effect binde both your Soveraignty, and your chiefeſt Court of Councell to caſt about for the preſervation and defence of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and every ſubject thereof in the liberty of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, keeping the bonds of civility and humanity; but (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at a farre diſtance) I perceive the old courſe is ſtill on foote, making ſides of Religion, and yokes for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on all ſides, wherein hath a world of blood beene ſpilt already, and much more will be if the ſame continue; Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, pride, and deluſion muſt bring forth their fruits where they grow, as doe all other things; for any hurt which befalls mankinde, let the pretence be what it will, floweth from thence, not from Chriſtian Religion; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt himſelfe, or any of his Diſciples upon Record in the New Teſtament, Apoſtles, or Evangeliſts, or others, did in a warlike way, either offend or defend themſelves for their Religions ſake.</p>
            <p>From former paſſages expreſſed in both the ſaid Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I have manifeſted ſufficient ground of boldneſſe, for ſpeaking to you Gods of the earth, which to rehearſe or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large is not improper; and for theſe cauſes following I am conſtrained yet further to move your greatneſſe, and being reaſonable therein, if ye being as gods deſpiſe me, I ſhall notwithſtanding fulfill the will of the Lord of Lords in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the ſpirits of error, though I periſh in the Worke
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100526:8"/>with the ſtrength of his encouragement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32.</p>
            <p>The firſt cauſe is this, I being by the Law of Humanity, or the nature of man, as deepely ingaged in the joy of the welfare, and ſorrow of the miſery thereof, though a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as having any intereſt in the power of enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or preventing either, am bound by the Law of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Humanitie and Chriſtianity to diſcover any thing or courſe tending to the accompliſhment of both, wherein is fulfilled the dutie of innocencie and uprightneſſe without feare (the roote of ſlavery and flattery) according to <hi>Marke</hi> 4.22. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.27, 28.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe is, for that there are and ſhall be many falſe Chriſts, falſe prophets, and falſe Teachers, as there be many Antichriſts, and falſe Churches, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of the New Teſtament, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.4, 5. alſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. Theſe are all one in ſpirit, and in that reſpect are of the devill, or as the devill himſelfe work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the miſery and confuſion of mankinde, in the greateſt meaſure that may be (the being of the world reſerved) and that according to the working of Sathan alſo, as in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, Serpent-like, and as in the full ſtrength of his Raigne, Dragon and Lyon-like, as is ſet forth, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9, 10. The Revelation ſets forth at large the ſpirit of Antichriſt, or falſe Church in his full portracture in every part and member of the ſaid body, from the ſixt Chapter to the latter end of the ſame booke; Now, although not in any meaſure inveſted in any power of ſuppreſſing any courſe of evill, and lifting up or inlivening any of good; yet as fully bound to diſcover both, by Chriſtian and naturall bonds as any, if all ſanctity and ſalvation both of ſoule and body be of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, Chriſt, and the Church or Kingdome of Chriſt, then of neceſſity is all miſchiefe of ſinne and miſery touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man of the ſpirit of the devill, Antichriſt and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and in ſhort, conſider each Kingdome is to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by the Doctrine and Learning, and the Diſcipline, or Government of the Spirit thereof; and ſo the Doctrine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100526:9"/>of the Goſpell teacheth touching matters of the ſoule (whoſe welfare is accompliſhed and inlarged by the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and peace of conſcience) Chriſtians to beare one with another, and the ſtronger to ſuffer for the weaker; knowing that none is maſter of his owne light or anothers, and in caſe of greateſt gainſaying, or perſecution for conſcience ſake, to ſuffer without reſiſtance, to doe good to all, even our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: in reſpect of that part of our well being, the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline therof is a government without Maſter or Lordſhip, as hath been formerly ſet forth, agreable to the Scriptures; as touching men in their perſons and eſtates, both teach and governe according to honeſty and ſobrietie to be iuſt and peaceable with all men, to ſuffer wrong in all, in caſe it be put upon them, the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Spirit of God, his Sonne and his Kingdome, or viſible Government tends all to the life of Juſtice, Peace, and Love, which is the way of ſalvation or preſervation, and perfection of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherein lived Chriſt and his diſciples upon Record in all long ſuffering, as the New Teſtament at large witneſſeth without reaching after worldly pompe, riches, and great command.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever profeſſeth to be Chriſts, and is contrary in ſpirit, is of the devill, and is falſe Chriſt, or Antichriſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a perſon or ſtate and members thereof, and if ſo viſible as holding forth Doctrine and Diſcipline under the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt, or being for him, in pretence, and teaching univerſall ſalvation to all of all Nations, with Nationall worſhip without Chriſts exception, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.23, 24, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34, 35. Teaching alſo for neceſſary Doctrine, commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men, outward conformity in matters of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, abſtinence from meates, and marriages, which God hath allowed; theſe be deluſions, and Doctrines of devills, Mockſoules, ſnares, and enemies to the peace and liberty of conſcience, and to the welfare thereof. As touching mens perſons and eſtates, teaching to ſacrifice the things belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thereto for ſinne and treſpaſſes, it is making Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100526:9"/>of men, no ſalvation but penance, a doctrine iſſuing from envie the mother of coveteouſneſſe, the roote of all evill, and is falſely called Chriſts, but properly is of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe Diſcipline and Government called Chriſts, in Nature, Maſterfull, Lordly, and compulſive, and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the practice of ſuch doctrine as aforeſaid, or the effect of any other by any externall violence, it is none of Chriſts, but Antichriſts, interrupting, yea by contrariety outing the obedience of faith which worketh by love, which onely is Chriſts, and onely acceptable to God, and moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with men, this is devilliſh and ſnaring the world, ſetting all together by the eares, that have more will to uſe violence to gaine the Maſterſhip of their owne conſcience (to whom it is moſt due next to God) then to be a ſlave to others therein, or to ſuffer as Chriſt, and his diſciples, keeping (though others breake them) the Lawes of civility, hence commeth contention the daughter of pride, who maketh men forget their maker and their fellowes wherein they ſhould be preſerved.</p>
            <p>The third cauſe is, that the generality of all or any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may not be nurſed up any longer in their wilfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion of being juſtified and ſaved in beleeving and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping as the Rulers beleeve and worſhip; wherein they diſcharge themſelves of any errour, and lay the blame of it upon their governours, who alſo out of their aſpiring pride to be as God and Chriſt; indeede (<hi>Adam</hi> like) are willing of it, yea they will have it ſo, cleane contrary to the doctrine of Chriſt and his Spirit, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.12. and <hi>v.</hi> 22, 23. wherein alſo is is practically contradicted with poſitive affirmation and reaſon, Chriſt &amp; his Diſciples it is apparent in Scripture, learned men to live by their owne faith, and to be able to give a reaſon thereof; it was their owne practiſe alſo, and not to uſe any Religion which was or ſhould be in faſhion amongſt the great ones; there is no ſin but it is again God, and every one ſhall give account to him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10.11,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100526:10"/>12. the King as he is King, and the ſubject, as a ſubject in matters of conſcience in point of Religion, all are as one with God, in that he reſpects no mans perſon, as is evident by Scripture, when pride and covetouſneſſe be well unmasked, the common people will have but ſmall incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to be ſo ready to deſtroy one another for that which Chriſt would have them ſaved, even for the faithfull and free uſe of their conſciences; but this is the effect of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing great ones, who give their power to him who teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to kill men for conſcience ſake, Chriſts and mans ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies both; is it not ſufficient and faithfull allegiance, for ſubiects to lay downe their lives and all that they have in defence of their Prince, for his preſervation in the freedome of his owne conſcience, and maintenance of civility, but that they muſt needs hazard themſelves contrary to civility and Chriſtianity to kill their fellowes becauſe they will not be ſlaves in that reſpect, wherein God accounts of them, and ſtiles them by the name of Kings and Prieſts, through the mediation of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. but woe to the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the earth, when Princes are led by thoſe that make a pray upon them and theirs. I meane the falſe Prophets who appeare in ſheepes cloathing but are inwardly wolves, rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after the world, and devouring ſoules and bodies for worldly ends, of which Chriſt gave faire warning, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15, 16. to make faire pretences for the Lord, and to ſpeake much in his name and for him, and to ſet the world on fire with the heat of warres, to the unſpeakeable ruine of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde for religion, ſheweth ſuch to be none of Chriſts Prophets, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.21. but rather to be the falſe teachers of pernitious wayes as they are rendred, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The fourth cauſe is, that King and Magiſtrates may be remembred, that they are not exempted from error of any nature incident to mankinde, and therefore their Lawes for Religion are no ſufficient bonds for conſcience, but in their owne particulars; Chriſts onely are ſufficient in that caſe. Secondly, that yee may be <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> remembred, although, as it were in Paradiſe for plenty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100526:10"/>of all things, yet as unapt, yee more than <hi>A</hi>-(by reaſon of the curſe) to be content with your allowance <hi>dam,</hi> who in his devilliſh reach to be as his maker, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned all the happineſſe which he had with allowance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That ye may be put in minde that God hath not laid upon you a charge impoſſible for you to undergoe, ſuch as the keeping of all your ſubjects in the upright uſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, being impoſſible for you to alter the ſame, being good or evill, or to account to God for them in the errors thereof, yea altogether unable to anſwer God for one of a thouſand in your owne, but that you preſerve and defend them, ordering their perſons and eſtates in civill demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, in the liberty and freedome of their conſcience, in which reſpect God only will take account of them, which ye might happily perform, if ye would leave Gods office to himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That although (as aforeſaid) in Paradiſe voide and not much ſenſible of afflicton, which learned <hi>David</hi> to keep Gods Law, (but rather fitted for the pleaſures of this life) ye may be remembred, that ye are the more ſubject to bee tempted by the devill and his inſtruments, who are led by his ſpirit of deluſion, and devouring, together with your own luſts, to be drawn through flattery, and undue elevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to oppreſſion in all reſpects, both inward and outward, and therefore have the more cauſe to be carefull to keepe your ſelves to the Lawes of modeſty, juſtice, and mercy, the beſt ornament for Gods Vicegerents, his ſpeciall offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or miniſters of Juſtice in humane affaires, wherein you ſhall comply with the King of Kings, and having him on your ſide, you will be ſtrong enough for all the world, in the way of defence for his and yours.</p>
            <p>In relation to theſe cauſes, and former paſſages, Moſt Noble King and high Court of Parliament, for the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and peace of the ſervice and worſhip of God, in all good conſcience, and for the ſame of man in all humanity; I can doe no leſſe then move you alwaies to put an end to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels for conſcience ſake, in granting all liberty within
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100526:11"/>bounds of civility, for the Tenent of going alI together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the eares in that caſe, is ſuggeſted upon falſe grounds; for did not men ſpoile each other for conſcience ſake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they have no law for from Chriſtianity, but from the ſpirit of the bottomleſſe pit; with what peace of conſcience, or colour of manhood, but in breach of civill peace, could they offer wrong to each other, which civill Lawes could not right without bloodſhed, but in caſe of murder or the like, double and treble the ſtrength of civill Lawes, which are the life and glory of all Kingdomes, and caſt away the image of Aegypt in both reſpects, temporall and ſpirituall bondage, for God hath branded it with evill for both, and let the lives of innocent men be free, according to the end of your Ordinance, and the Lawes thereof, as God hath appointed. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 9.10.</p>
            <p>Agree O ye powers of this Land, differ not for matters of this life, a little worldly honour or; maintenance; and if you will needs fall out and fight for your Religion, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in ſuch practiſe you croſſe the doctrine and actuall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of Chriſt and his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.10. If ye will be killing by way of offence or defence for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſake, take notice how ye diſobey the Law of the Spirit of God and Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.35, 36. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.34. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.60. Uncivill and inhumane actions, their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection belongs to the civill Authority, and untill that taken innocency, her part; conſcience then muſt ſatisfie thy ſelfe with the meaſure of Chriſt, and preceding Saints, if thou wilt actually and really as verbally in profeſſion follow Chriſt, and ſuch as are and were led by his Spirit; So lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving theſe paſſages with former to Royall and all right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, I remaine in all loyall ſubiection for the ſervice of God and man.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. Q.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100526:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
